Dwain Esper papers, 1928-1984
UCLA Library Special Collections
Dwain Esper papers
1928-1984
2301
UCLA Library Special Collections
1.8 linear ft. (2 document boxes and 1 oversize flatbox)
This collection primarily contains material belonging to movie producer and director Dwain Esper and his wife Hildagarde, including photographs, correspondence, business records, and advertisements, many of which are connected to Esper's movies and career.
Esper, Dwain
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Francis M. Woods and Kimberly Douglas, 2014.
Biography/History
Dwain Esper (1892-1982) was an American producer and director of exploitation films including Narcotic (1933), Maniac (1934), Marihuana (1936), and Sex Madness (1938). He is best-known as producer/distributor of the cult classic Reefer Madness (1936). In 1920, Esper married Hildagarde Stadie (1895-1993), who also wrote some of his movies.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of correspondence, legal and copyright material, photographs, and advertisements related to Dwain Esper's films, and well as business and financial records. Also present are some personal papers and photographs, as well as two sex education booklets by Hildagarde Esper. There is no material in this collection related to the film Reefer Madness.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Film-related papers
Series 2. Business records
Series 3. Personal material
Series 4. Photographs
Series 5. Advertisements
Series 6. Books
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7810170
Esper, Hildagarde; Renay, Liz; Exploitation films; Maniac (Motion picture: 1934)
Container List
- Series 1. Film-related papers., 1930-1984.
  Scope and Content
  Series includes copyright paperwork, legal agreements, publicity material, correspondence, ratings paperwork, and a script (Maniac) related to specific films produced by Esper or of interest to him. Also present is a small amount of financial records, primarily invoices for film prints, as well as correspondence regarding theatrical releases and M.J.W. Theatrical Enterprises, Inc. Advertisements for Esper's films are located in Series 5.
  - "Egyptian Picture.", undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - French Peep Show., 1972-1977. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Halfway to Hell., 1962. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hitler's Strange Love Life., 1973. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Alternative titles include Will It Happen Again? and Conform or Die.
  - How to Undress in Front of Your Husband., 1935, undated. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ingagi., 1930, 1950, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Maniac., undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Will It Happen Again?., 1948, 1975. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Alternative title for Hitler's Strange Love Life.
  - Legal/copyright records., 1950-1984. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence., 1950, 1971-1976. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial records., 1972-1973. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 2. Business records., 1957-1970.
  Includes financial records, correspondence, and reports relating to other business or real estate dealings of Dwain and Hildagarde Esper.
  - Tempest Mining Corporation., 1970. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Warm Springs Lead-Zinc Prospect., 1957. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Financial records., 1957-1964. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series 3. Personal material., 1942-[1984].
  Series includes Esper's membership cards, notes. clippings, entertainment magazines, and ephemera. Also present are photographs (box 1), clippings, and posters related to cult film star and burlesque performer Liz Renay (1926-2007).
  - Notes., 1982, undated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Membership cards., 1942-1969. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings., 1945-[1984]. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Magazines and ephemera., 1945-1979, undated. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Liz Renay material., 1970s. (Box 1, Folder 18, Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series 4. Photographs., [1900s]-1960.
  Series contains primarily reprints of historic photographs of 20th century figures and events, including Adolf Hitler, Eva Braun, Benito Mussolini, and Vladimir Lenin, as well as Nazi concentration camps. Also present are film stills from Forbidden Adventure, images of marquees of theaters screening Esper's films, and family photographs.
  - Hitler/Nazi Germany., undated. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Buchenwald/concentration camps., undated. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Eva Braun., undated. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Mussolini/Italy., undated. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lenin/USSR., undated. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Other historical figures., undated. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Forbidden Adventure stills., undated. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Theater marquees., undated. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Film stills (non-Esper)., undated. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Family photographs., [1900s]-1960. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series 5. Advertisements., Undated.
  Series consists of lobby cards for Forbidden Adventure and mock-ups of advertisements for other Esper films, as well as some promotional material for a few non-Esper films.
  - Forbidden Adventure., undated. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Narcotic., undated. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hitler's Strange Love Life., undated. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes one full-size poster.
  - Other films., undated. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ads (relief mats)., undated. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Series 6. Books., 1934-1948. (Box 3)
  Contains two sex education booklets by Hildagarde Esper: Your Sex Questions Answered... What Every Modern Mother and Father Should Know (1934), and Facts of Life: What Every Adult Should Know about Sex and Its Relation to Human Happiness (1948). Also present is The Book of Poe: Tales, Criticism, Poems (1934).